Guide to the Robert Grenier Papers
Department of Special Collections
- Series VI. RG Critical Writings 1960 - 1998, Being notes, papers, essays, reviews, verse commentaries, speculative jottings, etc., dated/ chronologized and counted (by pages of text) in folders. 1 box.
  - C. RG Critical Writings, 1970 - 1998
    - 1. Background Materials re publication of this 1 (Box 015)
      - RG ts. letter to Curtis Faville, 1970 Dec 6, (xerox) (4 pp. total)
        (speaking to CF's writing & soliciting contribution to this 1, w/ RG poems from "Fall/Winter Family Home" & commentary thereon)
    - 2. RG ts. of "ROBERT CREELEY: A QUICK GRAPH: Collected Notes & Essays, Four Seasons, 1970", RG review pub. in this 1 w/ RG holograph revisions 1971 Winter, (6 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 3. RG ts. of note "ON SPEECH" w/ RG holograph revisions (1970 Dec), (pub. in this 1, Winter 1971), xerox of same & xerox of "ON SPEECH" as it occurs in In The American Tree, ed. Ron Silliman (National Poetry Foundation, 1986) (3 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 4. RG ts. of "ROBERT CREELEY, PIECES, Scribners, 1969", RG review pub. in this 1 (1971 Winter), w/ RG holograph revisions (5 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 5. RG ts. of note on "GERTRUDE STEIN: Lectures in America, Beacon, 1957 (first pub., Random House, 1935)" consisting principally of quotation from GS text, pub. in this 1 (1971 Winter), w/ RG holograph revisions (3 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 6. RG ts. of "EDWARD LEAR, The Complete Nonsense Book, Duffield & Co., NY 1912", w/ RG holograph revisions, pub. in this 1 (1971 Winter), (1 p. total) (Box 015)
    - 7. RG ts. of notes on writing/sequencing of poems (apparently from Lanesville, MA, 1970 - 1971), (xerox of (lost?) RG ts. w/ 1999 xerox of same) (2 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 8. RG ts. of "WILLIAM CARLOS WILLIAMS: Spring And All, Frontier Press, 1970 (first pub., Contact, 1923)", RG review pub. in this 2 (1971 Fall), (6 pp. total) w/ RG holograph revisions (Box 015)
    - 9. RG ts. of "NOTES ON COOLIDGE, OBJECTIVES, ZUKOFSKY, ROMANTICISM, AND &", pub. in STATIONS, No. 5 (1978 Winter), (22 pp. total) (Box 015)
      A Symposium on Clark Coolidge, ed. Ron Silliman, & in IN THE AMERICAN TREE (National Poetry Foundation, 1986), ed. Ron Silliman.
      - RG ts. first draft w/ RG holograph additions, 1975 Nov 12
      - RG ts. final draft, (xerox)
    - 10. Materials related to RG's edition of Robert Creeley's Selected Poems, Scribner's, 1976, (29 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG ts. of RG introduction to RC Selected Poems (omitted by Scribner's editorial dept. w/out notice to RG or RC) & xerox of same, pub. in boundary 2, Vol. 6, No. 3/Vol.7, No. 1 (Spring/Fall 1978), 1975 Nov 6
      - RG ts. of table of contents to RC Selected Poems (altered by Scribner's editorial dept. w/out notice to RG or RC), pub. in boundary 2 (1978 Spring - 1978 Fall), (xerox)
      - Xeroxes of correspondence amongst Burroughs Mitchell & Charles Scribner of Scribner's, RC & RG concerning botched book (1975 Oct 16 - 1976 Nov 4):
        - BM to RG, 1975 Oct 16
        - BM to RG, 1975 Nov 19
        - BM to RG, 1975 Dec 3
        - RC to CS, 1976 Oct 29
        - Patricia Cristol (editor at Scribner's) to RG, 1976 Oct 29
        - RG to BM, 1976 Nov 4
      - Xerox of RG's "A PACKET FOR ROBERT CREELEY", pub. in boundary 2, issue titled "ROBERT CREELEY: A GATHERING", Vol. 6, No. 3/Vol. 7, No. 1 (1978 Spring/Fall), ed. William V. Spanos:
        - RG letter to William V. Spanos, 1977 Feb 5
        - RG suppressed/excluded introduction to RC Selected Poems, dated 1975 Nov 6
        - RG original table of contents for RC Selected Poems
        - RG selection of "136 separate poems from SENTENCES: for Robert Creeley"
    - 11. RG ts. of RG selection of passages from John Keats, Louis Zukofsky & RG forming basis for discussing 'lyric poem', ca. 1975, (1 p. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 12. RG holograph note beginning "the space between letters..." ca. 1975, (1 p. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 13. RG holograph notes on 'state of American poetry' beginning "Poetry is measure..."ca. 1975, (3 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 14. RG ts. 'cover letter' to poetry editor at Houghton Mifflin re RG poetry, enclosed w/ ts. of "Fall/Winter Family Home" (later collected in Series, This Press, 1978), 1976 Oct 27, (xerox) (2 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 15. RG ts. of note on Larry Eigner's work, "THREE POSSIBILITIES --- for Larry Eigner", dated 1977 Oct 5, w/ 2 pp. of RG holograph draft & xerox of RG ts. letter to Bruce Andrews, ed. of L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E, October 9, 1977 re note (11 pp. total) (Box 015)
      (apparently designed for L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E magazine feature on LE, Feb. 1978, but doesn't appear there--Why?)(unpublished?)
    - 16. Xerox of RG essay, "MYTH", as pub. in Archai magazine, No. 1 w/ RG holograph revisions1978 Spring, (8 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 17. RG ts. of note on Louis Zukofsky, "THINK SUN AND SEE SHADOW", pieced from lines of LZ's, w/ xerox of same, pub. in Zukofsky feature in L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E magazine, Vol. 1, No. 4 (1978 August) & reprinted in The L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E Book, ed. AnDBews & Bernstein (So.Ill.U. Press, 1984), (2 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 18. RG note on Keats' sound, "Hedge-crickets sing", pub. in L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E magazine, Vol. 1, No. 5 (1978 October) & reprinted in The L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E Book, ed. Andrews & Bernstein (So. Ill. U. Press, 1984), (9 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG initial ts. w/ RG holograph revisions
      - RG final version ts. (w/ xerox of same)
    - 19. RG note on Gertrude Stein's method, "TENDER BUTTONS", pub. in LANGUAGE magazine, Vol. 1, No. 6 (1978 Dec) & reprinted in The L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E Book, ed. Andrews & Bernstein (So. Ill. U. Press, 1984), (6 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG final version ts. (w/ xerox of same)
    - 20. RG holograph notes on three texts from Gertrude Stein's Tender Buttons, "A Carafe, That Is A Blind Glass,""Glazed Glitter" & "Roastbeef" from ca. 1978 Oct/Nov, unfinished (19 pp. total) (Box 015)
      (intended for L=A=N=G=U=A=GE magazine but unpublished)
    - 21. RG 'review' of Lyn Hejinian's WRITING IS AN AID TO MEMORY (The Figures, 1978), pub. in L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E magazine, Vol. 2, No. 8 1979 June, (6 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG final version ts. (w/ xerox of same)
    - 22. RG holograph note on function of phrase, "AND A" from early 1980's, (6 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 23. RG holograph notes on combinations of "3" from early 1980's, (2 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 24. RG materials re publication of In The American Tree, ed. Ron Silliman (National Poetry Foundation (1986), (41 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RS ts. letter to RG, 1981 Sept 17, proposing RG selections for anthology
      - RG counter-proposal/holograph list of RG selections
      - Some RG ms. material for anthology:
        - RG tss. of "WINTRY", "WARM", "A SEQUENCE / 28 SEPARATE POEMS FROM SENTENCES"
        - Xerox of "Sticky Fingers" (in Series, This, 1978)
        - Various RG ts. drafts of RG bio w/ holograph revisions (& xeroxes of same)
      - Two RS ts. form letters to RG enclosing galleys
      - Galley proofs of "ON SPEECH" & "NOTES ON COOLIDGE, OBJECTIVES, ZUKOFSKY, ROMANTICISM, AND &"
    - 25. RG holograph copies/extractions from RG 1980-81 notebooks 1999 Mar, (4 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      - RG note "THE PYRAMIDS" from 1980 Fall notebook
      - RG note on Olson's "can one nunc nine", called "THAT" from 1981 Jan notebook
      - RG "Note on E.P.'s 'Mauberley'" from 1981 Feb notebook
    - 26. RG ts. 'review' of Robert Creeley's Later (New Directions, 1979) from ca. 1981, pub. in L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E magazine, Vol. 4 (Open Letter, 5th Series, No. 1, Winter 1982), (14 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG original ts. (w/ xerox of same)
      - Xerox of 'review' as pub. in L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E magazine
    - 27. RG 'review' of Bernadette Mayer's Midwinter Day (Turtle Island, 1982), (3 pp. total) (Box 015)
      (unpublished; declined by Poetry Flash w/out acknowledgement of receipt of ts.)
      - RG holograph draft
      - Xerox of RG final ts., dated 1983 Jan 15
    - 28. RG ts. of "STATEMENT ON TEACHING" w/ RG holograph revisions, written for University of California Summer Seminar application, 1983, (1 p. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 29. RG note on Ron Silliman's Tjanting, dated 1983 Aug 4, pub. in Silliman issue of The Difficulties, Vol. 2, No. 2 (1985), (4 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG ts. w/ holograph revision (& xerox of same)
    - 30. RG holograph letter to Robert Creeley re "weights & durations of 'syllable'" etc., (xerox) (2 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 31. RG verse commentary re Robert Creeley's Mirrors (New Directions, 1983), pub. in RG's Phantom Anthems (0 Books, 1986), The Line in Postmodern Poetry, ed. Frank & Sayre (U. of Illinois Press, 1988) & The Norton Anthology of Postmodern American Poetry, ed. Paul Hoover (Norton, 1993), (2 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - Xerox of version in The Line in Postmodern Poetry
        (bad 'translation' into a conventional format)
      - RG finished ts. (from history of making of Phantom Anthems, elsewhere in RG Archive), (82% reduction)
        (i.e. poem as it should appear)(see IX.C.II below)
    - 32. RG unfinished essay, "SPRING GREEN / for WCW" ca. 1983, (16 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph first draft & second draft
      - RG ts. third draft (& xerox of same w/ holograph changes)
      - RG ts. fourth draft w/ holograph revisions (abandoned)
    - 33. RG note on Stephen Rodefer's play, "TENNYSON", w/ program indicating performance by SR at 80 Langton Street in San Francisco, November 20, 1983, pub. in Jimmy & Lucy's House of "K", No. 2 1984 August, (15 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph initial draft
      - RG ts. final draft (w/ xerox), dated 1984 Jan 14
    - 34. RG holograph letter to Joanne Kyger, 1984 August 16, (xerox) (8 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      Written at beach near Pigeon Point in San Mateo County re method of poems in A Day At The Beach (Roof Books, 1985) & Costanoans/possible archaic sources.
    - 35. RG note on/review of Lyn Hejinian's REDO (Salt-Works Press, 1984) dated 1985 Apr 1, (30 pp. total) (Box 015)
      Pub. in Jimmy & Lucy's House of "K", No. 4 (1985)
      - RG holograph first draft of note on REDO
      - RG ts. second draft w/ RG holograph revisions
      - RG ts. third draft & two xeroxes of same w/ RG holograph revisions
      - RG ts. fourth/final draft
      - RG packet w/ holograph note to Ben Friedlander, ed. of Jimmy & Lucy's, enclosing RG note on REDO & the following RG poems (most in Phantom Anthems) (xerox)
        - "MORANDI", "FOR WINDOWS / for Kit", "EXCLAMATION POINT / for Ron Silliman", "UNBENDING LEGS / for Alastair" & "EASTER ROSES / for Ken Irby"
    - 36. Three RG notes from: ca. 1985 Oct, All holograph (4 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      - "BOB/SELF-PORTRAIT"
      - "CREATION"
      - Note relating & differentiating "sequence" & "series" beginning "3 2 2 1. ."
    - 37. RG sketch on Kenneth Irby, original ts. called "A LITTLE LIGHT FROM THE BOARDERS" from ca. l985, (6 pp. total) (Box 015)
      (apparently unpublished, though possibly intended for Irby issue of some magazine?)
    - 38. RG collage re Kenneth Irby/account of relation between KI & RG over time, called "VOCALIC COTTONWOODS", pub. as insert in Jimmy & Lucy's House of "K", No. 5 (1985), (13 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph first draft
      - RG ts. second draft (w/ xerox of same)
      - Three taped-together cut-up versions (w/ xeroxed third draft made from cut-ups)
      - RG final draft/xerox master & two finished images made (xeroxed) from same (including grey-paper version, signed "Robert Grenier" across image, as text occurs in Jimmy & Lucy's insert)
    - 39. RG testament, "FOR TOM RAWORTH ALIVE / I SAW MY POEMS" incorporating/accounting for image of Max Ernst photocollage "Une Semaine de Bont" pub. in _________ (1934), dated 1986 Feb 22, (16 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph first draft
      - Four xerox versions of Ernst photocollage
      - RG final ts. version, w/ Ernst image as p. 3, (xerox)
    - 40. RG note on David Bromige, "TO SEE OURSELVES AS OTHERS SEE US", pub. in The Difficulties, Vol. 3, No. 1 (1987, Bromige issue) dated 1986 Aug 4, (8 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph first draft
      - RG ts. second draft (w/ xerox of same)
      - RG third draft (xerox of second draft w/ holograph revisions)
      - RG ts. final draft (w/ xerox of same)
    - 41. RG holograph note "ON SPEECH / 1986 / for Jay Ryneck", (8 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 42. RG comment, holograph, on passage from Walt Whitman later called "This Compost", incorporating xerox of Whitman verse, possibly pub. in Jimmy & Lucy's House of "K", No? 1986 (?), (7 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 43. RG note on Alice Notley's Parts Of A Wedding, pub. in Sulfur 20, Vol. 7, No. 2 (1987) & reprinted (w/ Notley work) in 0 One, ed. Leslie Scalapino (0 Books, 1988) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph first draft, (7 pp. total)
      - RG ts. final draft, (w/ xerox of same) (2 pp. total)
    - 44. RG 'review' of Anselm Hollo's PICK UP THE HOUSE! (Coffee House Press, 1987), called "I HAD NO IDEA / PICK UP THE HOUSE!",, pub. in Sulfur 23, Vol. 8, No. 2 (1988) dated 1987 Oct 10, (31 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph first Draft
      - RG ts. second Draft, w/ RG holograph revisions
      - RG ts. final Draft
    - 45. RG left-handed holograph note called "RESULTS OF PRINTING LEFT-HANDED IN OCTOBER / for Alastair" from 1987 Oct, (3 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 46. RG holograph note beginning "--time in the work...", as pub. in CHUMOLUNGMA GLOBE, No. 1 (1987 Halloween), ed. Schelling & Friedlander, (xerox from mag.) (1 p. total) (Box 015)
    - 47. RG holograph notes on Kit Robinson's essay, "Song" (where pub.?) from 1987 Fall, (4 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      (see two KR/RG Conversations in V.C. above)
    - 48. RG DBeam notation, 1987 Dec beginning "Michael Palmer gives DB & me ride.. .", (RG holograph) (4 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 49. RG holograph notes on Charles Olson's "The literal and the numeral are the same" & on the word "explicit" from ca. 1987, (2 Pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 50. RG note on use of 'lines' in poetry, called "LINE", pub. in The Line in Postmodern Poetry, ed. Frank & Sayre (U. of Illinois Press, 1988), (7 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph first Draft (partial)
      - RG ts. final Draft, incorporating RG poem "BACH FIVE / for Lyn Hejinian" (in Phantom Anthems, 0 Books, 1986)
      - Two xeroxes of final Draft (one w/ crossed-out RG holograph revisions)
    - 51. RG holograph letter to Lyn Hejinian, 1988 May 26, (xerox) (4 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      re LH text My Life & recent LH poems
    - 52. RG 'Contributor's Note' intended for UP LATE, poetry anthology ed. AnDBei CoDBescu (4 Walls 8 Windows, 1988) dated 1988 Aug 4, (6 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph first Draft
      - RG ts. second Draft (w/ xerox of same)
      - RG third Draft (second Draft w/ RG holograph revisions)
      - RG ts. final Draft (w/ xerox of same)
    - 53. RG exchange w/ Jack Clarke & Robert Creeley re Clarke's From Feathers To Iron (Tomboucto/Convivio, 1987), (42 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph letter to JC re From Feathers To Iron, October 6, 1988 (xerox)
      - JC letter to RG, 1988 Dec 20, (JC ts.), enclosing
      - JC's transcription/revision of RG Oct 6 letter
      - RG letter to Creeley, January 13, 1989 (xerox), enclosing xerox of RG October 6 letter to JC, (RG holograph)
      - RC letter to RG, 1989 Jan 18, (RC ts.)
      - RG holograph letter to JC, 1989 Jan 8, (xerox)
    - 54. RG holograph notes on translation, preparatory to public discussion w/ Anselm Hollo at New College, 1988 Nov 28, (audiotape & videotape in V.A. & V.B. above), w/flyer for event (7 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 55. RG holograph essay, "ON TRANSLATION / for R.W. Emerson" from ca. 1988, (4 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 56. Materials from three RG grant applications (unfunded) (Box 015)
      - RG Guggenheim application (for 1981 - 1982), w/ RG ts. bio, project proposal & list of publications
      - RG NEH 1982 Summer Seminar application, w/ RG project statement, (xerox)
      - RG California Arts Council application, 1988 Sept
        (unsatisfactory attempt to 'translate' holograph Drawing poems from start of r h y m m s project to ts.: ms. had to be ts. to be 'poems' for purposes of application)
    - 57. RG holograph note on Larry Eigner's areas / lights / heights, ed. Ben Friedlander (Roof Books, 1989), (xerox) (2 pp. total) (unpublished?) (Box 015)
    - 58. RG holograph letter to Kenneth Irby, 1989 Aug 17, called "QUESTIONS FOR UNCLE KEN", re 'uses' of the past etca., (xerox) (8 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
    - 59. RG color holograph autobiographical/critical poem called "POET FELT" from ca. 1989, pub. in Tyuonyi 6/7 (1990) in "Patterns/Contexts/Time: A Symposium on Contemporary Poetry", ed. Foss & Bernstein, (1 p. total) (Box 015)
    - 60. RG exchange w/ Douglas Messerli re inclusion of RG material in FROM THE OTHER SIDE OF THE CENTURY: A New American Poetry 1960 - 1990 (Sun & Moon, 1994), ed. Douglas Messerli, (102 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - DM ts. letter to RG, 1990 Jan 29
        Proposing both RG selection of 10 pp. for anthology & that RG send "selection, however large or small, of ... new work"
      - RG packet of poems sent DM for anthology, 1990 Mar 10
      - RG ts. letter to DM, inquiring re anthology packet previously sent, & enclosing ms. of "about 2/3rds" of book of RG critical writings w/ outline of contents of proposed volume 1990 Mar 28, (xerox)
      - RG ts. letter to DM, inquiring re selections for anthology/book of critical writings 1992 Sept 29, (copy)
      - DM print-out letter to RG, re anthology 1993 July 26
      - RG ts. letter to DM, re selection for anthology, enclosing RG poems from Phantom Anthems & What I Believe 1993 Aug 17, (xerox)
      - DM print-out letter to RG, 1994 Jan 9
      - DM print-out letter to RG, 1994 Mar 2, w/ proofs
      - RG ts. letter to DM,, returning page proofs for anthology 1994 Mar 5, (xerox) (w/ RG-marked proofs)
    - 61. RG verse memoir of Robert Lowell teaching at Harvard College, written in response to Kathleen Spivack's call for contributions to her book-in-progress, THE GEM LIKE FLAME, from 1990 Nov, (never used) (11 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - KS form letter to RG, 1990 Oct 24
      - RG holograph letter to KS, 1990 Nov 14, (xerox)
      - RG holograph color Drawing poem/letter, (xerox of p. 1)
      - RG ts. final version of verse memoir, (unpublished)
        (unfortunately not used by KS, for reasons unspecified)
    - 62. Two RG verse appreciations of the work of Kit Robinson, esp. KR's The Champagne of Concrete (Potes & Poets Press, 1991) from late 1990, (5 pp. total) (unpublished?) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph Draft of "TO MR KIT ROBINSON"
      - Two xeroxes of RG final ts. version of "TO MR. KIT ROBINSON"
      - Two xeroxes of RG ts. 'second-take', also called "TO MR. KIT ROBINSON" ("for Gunnar Harding")
    - 63. RG back-cover note for Pat Reed's Kismet (0 Books, 1990), (xerox of RG ts.) (1 p. total) (Box 015)
    - 64. Materials related to genesis of Leslie Scalapino's introduction to RG's What I Believe Transpiration/Transpiring Minnesota (0 Books, 1991), (7 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph letter to LS, re LS Draft of introduction (xerox) 1991 May 4, enclosing
      - LS ts. Draft of introduction, w/ RG holograph notes & suggested/possible revisions, (xerox)
      - LS ts. second Draft of introduction, w/ RG holograph annotations & suggested/possible revisions/additions
      - Darkened xerox of LS ts. final Draft of introduction, beginning "Robert Grenier's 'scrawl'..", Two acid-free pages which occur on inside covers of actual text box
        (reprinted, w/ additional text, in LS's Objects in the Terrifying Tense / Longing from Taking Place, Roof Books, 1993)
    - 65. RG ts. description of RG's What I Believe Transpiration/Transpiring Minnesota, written for publicity purposes in 1991, (1 p. total) (Box 015)
    - 66. RG ts. of 'review' of Joanne Kyger's Just Space (Black Sparrow, 1991), dated 1991 Nov 19, (2 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 67. RG ts. of back-cover note for 8-Ball, words by Jack Collum/monoprints by Donald Guravich (Dead Metaphor Press, 1992) (xerox), w/ RG ts. letter to publisher, Richard Wilmarth, dated 1992 June 6, (xerox) (2 pp. total) (Box 015)
    - 68. RG holograph 'after-notes' re RG lecture at Naropa Institute, "Drawing Form Nature", 1992 July, (6 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      (see V.A.26, V.C.15 above)
    - 69. RG exchange w/ Paul Hoover, ed. of POSTMODERN AMERICAN POETRY (Norton, 1994), (19 pp. total) (Box 015)
      Re inclusion of RG material there.
      - PH print-out permissions request to RG proposing selection of RG poems for anthology, 1992 July 28
      - RG holograph letter to PH, 1992 Aug 16, (xerox)
      - Xeroxes of alternate selection of poems from RG's Phantom Anthems for use in anthology
      - RG ts. letter to PH, 1992 Sept 13re selection (xerox) & rationale for same
      - PH print-out letter to RG, 1992 Sept 15
      - PH print-out letter to RG, 1992 Sept 17
      - RG ts. letter to PH, 1992 Sept 22(xerox) approving publication of four poems from Phantom Anthems
    - 70. RG ts. back-cover note for Jim McCrary's West of Mass (Tansy Press, 1992), (xerox) (1 p. total) (Box 015)
    - 71. RG note "HOT AFTERNOONS HAVE BEEN IN BOLINAS / for Eli Siegel", dated 1993 Jan 23, (11 pp. total) (Box 015)
      Pub. in 0, No. 4 (1993) (Subliminal Time), ed. Leslie Scalapino & reprinted in: that:, Second Series, No. 1 (1996) as part of "GRENIER TALK"
      - RG ts. first Draft
      - RG second Draft, (xerox of first Draft w/ RG holograph revisions)
      - RG ts. final Draft
      - Leslie Scalapino holograph letter to RG, enclosing proofs of note for 0, No. 4 1993 May
      - RG-marked proofs, as returned to LS, (xerox)
      - Version of note, as pub. in 0, No. 4, (xerox)
    - 72. Two RG letters to Albert Gelpi re AG's account of the American poetic tradition in The Tenth Muse (Cambridge U. Press, 1991) & A Coherent Splendor (Cambridge, 1987) & projected third volume (on 'Postmodernism'), (25 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - AG holograph letter to RG, 1993 Oct 26, enclosing two vols. noted above
      - RG holograph letter to AG, 1993 Oct 28, (xerox)
      - RG holograph letter to AG, 1993 Nov 10, (xerox)
    - 73. RG holograph letter to Robert Creeley, 1993 Nov 1, (xerox) (4 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      Re 'sonata form'/3-line stanzas.
    - 74. RG ts. introductory note for Jerry Estrin's Rome, A Mobile Home (Roof Books, 1993), (never used) (2 pp. total) (Box 015)
      - RG ts. final Draft, w/ RG holograph annotations, dated 1993 June 15, (w/ xerox of same)
    - 75. Three RG letters to Charles Bernstein re CB's writing, (25 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      - RG holograph letter to CB,1986 July 16, (xerox)
        Re CB's Content's Dream (Sun & Moon Press, 1986)
      - RG holograph letter to CB, 1988 Feb 4, (xerox)
        Re CB's Artifice of Absorption (Paper Air, 1987)
      - RG holograph letter to CB, 1994 Apr 23, (xerox)
        Re CB's Dark City (Sun & Moon Press, 1994)
    - 76. RG note on "2000 / for Johannes Brahms' Horn Trio (1865)", (5 pp. total) (unpublished) (Box 015)
      - Leslie Davis form letter to RG proposing contribution to book centered on theme "poetry in the year 2000", 1994 May 15
        (book never appeared)
      - RG ts. letter to LD, 1994 May 18 (xerox), enclosing
      - RG ts. final Draft of "2000", (w/ xerox of same)